Finding Aid for Harry G. Kipke papers, 1917-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harry G. Kipke papers 1917-1938
Kipke, Harry G., 1899-1972
3.5 linear feet, 1 oversize bundle, and 2 oversize folders
851601 Aa 2; UAm; UAl
Varsity athlete, 1921-1924, and head football coach, 1929-1937, at the University of Michigan. Papers include football playbooks, scrapbooks detailing his athletic career, and photograph album of Kipke, university scenes, and athletic events.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Harry G. Kipke (donor no. 5414 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kipke was born March 26, 1899 in Lansing, Michigan. As a high school athlete, Kipke earned thirteen letters, four each in football, basketball and football, and one in track. Entering the University of Michigan in 1921, Kipke became Michigan's first nine letter man as he won three Varsity awards in football, basketball and baseball. As a football player, he excelled as a halfback and as the team's punter. In 1922, he earned a place on Walter Camp's All-American team and in 1923 was selected captain of the Michigan squad.
Graduating from the University in 1924, Kipke took a position at the University of Missouri as head baseball and assistant football coach but returned to Michigan the following year as an assistant coach in football, basketball and baseball. After three years in these capacities, he accepted the post as head football coach at Michigan State College, but stayed only one season, then returned to the University of Michigan as head football coach.
Head coach from 1929 to 1937 compiled a 46-26-4 overall record and a 27-21-2 record in conference games. After finishing 8th the conference in1929, Kipke's teams won or shared the conference title from 1930-1933 and were named national champions in 1932 and 1933.
Thereafter, his teams began losing, managing just a 6-18 overall record and winning only two conference games from 1934 to 1937. Following the 1937 season Kipke was dismissed and replaced by Herbert O. "Fritz" Crisler.
Kipke then began a long career with the Coca-Cola company and also served as regent of the University of Michigan, 1940-1947. Kipke was inducted into the College Football Hall of Fame in 1958.
He died September 14, 1972.
The Kipke papers document his career as a high school athlete in Lansing, Michigan; as a varsity football, basketball and baseball player at the University of Michigan; and as head football coach at the University of Michigan. The collection include football playbooks, scrapbooks detailing his athletic career, game films from the 1933 season, a football instructional film, and photograph album of Kipke, university scenes, and athletic events. The papers have been organized into the following series: Scrapbooks, Football Playbooks, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Football--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Scrapbooks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Football--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Football.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks
  - circa 1917-1924 (Box 1)
  - 1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - circa 1932 (Box 2)
  - circa 1934 (Box 2)
  - circa 1935 (Box 2)
  - circa 1937, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1938 (Box 2)
    (regarding Kipke's dismissal as coach)
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous loose clippings, manuscript of an article, and football play diagrams (Box 2)
- Football Playbooks
  - Various teams, 1924-1929, 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Publication: "Michigan's Offense; Showing Block and Timing of Plays" by Harry Kipke (Sayger Sports Syndicate, 1934) (Folder UAm)
  - Playbook, 1936-1937 seasons (Bundle 1)
    (oversize bundle)
- Visual materials
  - Photographs
    - Panoramic view of the Michigan-Ohio State football game, October 21, 1933 (Folder UAl)
    - Team photographs of University of Michigan baseball, basketball, and football teams in which Kipke was either a player or assistant coach (football), 1922-1937, 13 photographs (Folder UAm)
    - Photograph album of Kipke, University scenes, and University of Michigan athletics, 1921-1924 (Box 3)
    - Kipke as football player (Box 3)
    - Kipke miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Drawing
    - Pencil portrait of Kipke by R. Lovell (Box 3)
  - Motion pictures
    - Football game films, 1933 (U-M v. Ohio State, partial; U-M v. Cornell, partial) (Box 4)
      (include two 3/4 inch U-Matic use copies, different speeds; and betacam master)
    - Modern football fundamentals (Box 4)
      (include 3/4 in. U-matic use copy)
    - Football films with images from a California vacation trip (Box 4)